Okay, בוקר טוב Boker Tov everybody, good איסרו חג. Isru Chag. Today's
דף Daf is קל"ב, Kuf Lamed Bet, 132... or that's our דף.
Daf. We'll pick up on קל"א, Kuf Lamed Aleph, עמוד ב', Amud
Bet, four lines down in the wide lines. Okay, start of a
new topic.
אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל, Amar Rav Yehuda Amar Shmuel, הכותב כל
נכסיו לאשתו לא עשה אלא אפוטרופא. Hakoseiv Kol Nechasav L'Ishto, Lo Asah
Ela Apitropas. If somebody basically writes... the reason we're bringing in this
ruling, yeah yeah, the reason we're bringing in this ruling is because
if you remember the גמרא Gemara earlier wanted to know like for
רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא Rabbi Yochanan ben Broka when you redistribute your
property amongst your heirs, if that works even when a person is
healthy or only when a person's on their deathbed, only when they're
in the context of זה היה ביום הנחילו את בניו, Zeh Haya
B'yom Hanchilo Es Banav, the day that you are seen as in
the process of bequeathing your property, that the person is in the
process of dying. Or did it work even if the person is
nice and healthy and whatever, he can reassign his heirs. So that
question, are we saying the following law only in the case of
a שכיב מרע Shchiv Meira or even by a ברי? Bari? Only
a person on deathbed or even a healthy person? Is the law
we're going to ask about a number of different הלכות? Halachos? So
that's why we're bringing together a couple of different הלכות Halachos in
order to get eventually to the same question. Does this apply only
to a שכיב מרע Shchiv Meira or does it apply even to
a healthy person? Okay, so that's why we're introducing this הלכה. Halacha.
And we'll introduce a number of other הלכות Halachos that are going
to get us to a similar question about their scope. So this
הלכה Halacha is in the name of רב יהודה Rav Yehuda in
the name of שמואל, Shmuel, that a man basically and again, the
default case is he's on his deathbed, a שכיב מרע. Shchiv Meira.
So it's sort of seen in that context of him getting ready
to distribute all of his property. And he writes to his wife,
I'm hereby granting all of my property to my wife. Okay, so
wonderful, now she's got all of the property, what about all of
his kids, what about all of his heirs, his natural heirs? So
we are going to interpret this as he did not really gift
the property to his wife, he made her rather an executor of
his estate, an אפוטרופא. Apitropas. He made her in charge of you
know, of the property afterwards, she would be the one that would
handle you know, paying the bills and if there was any decisions
maybe about how to divide the estate amongst the heirs. So she
would be the sort of like overseer and the executor, but she
actually would not be have been awarded any of her own personal
property. So that's how we're going to read it, okay?
So like you said, this is
sort of ירושה Yerusha vs מתנה? Matana? Right, okay. Now the גמרא
Gemara later says, right, the גמרא Gemara later says that this is
one of the הלכות Halachos that the Rabbis made כהלכתא בלא טעמא,
K'Hilchosa B'Lo Taama, like a הלכה Halacha without any good reason, arbitrarily.
We're thinking that we can get into a person's head, you know,
there could be a dozen different reasons why a person does this.
And we are just making a general rule that we're going to
interpret his words against their surface meaning and we're not going to
say it was really a gift, we're going to say what he's
really trying to do is a way of saying I'm authorizing her
over the estate. And that's in a way in order that his
kids should then honor their mother, or honor his wife. We'll see
later about whether it's only their mother or not. Anyway, after his
death, because now she's going to have authority about how to distribute
the property. Of course, they would honor her a lot more if
she owned all the property. Okay, but anyway, but that's how we're
going to read it, alright? So that's the הלכה. Halacha. So let's
get into it a minute. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara wants
to understand the scope of this. And that's כל נכסיו, Kol Nechasav,
all of the property. Since it's so absolute, we're going to read
it this way, that it was pro forma and what he really
was doing was making her an executor. So פשיטא Peshita says גמרא,
Gemara, it's obvious that בנו הגדול לא עשה אלא אפוטרופא, Beno Hagadol
Lo Asah Ela Apitropas, that don't just think that this is some
sort of thing we have against the wife. If he did the
exact same thing with his eldest son, he awarded all of his
property to his eldest son.
To the בכור? Bechor? Right? Maybe not.
What do you mean?
Maybe a daughter, right?
Right, well no, we're talking about, oh right, you mean if he
had a daughter before, that's correct. Anyway, so he awarded all of
his property to the eldest son, we read it the same way,
that we see this as he wants the other brothers to honor
the son, he wants to give this son this role of the
executor and the overseer, but he doesn't really want to disinherit everybody
else. So probably what it's more about is a desire not to
read that what somebody's doing is disinheriting all the other heirs. So
when it's כל נכסיו, Kol Nechasav, we're going to read it this
way. Now that's both his wife and his son, where his kids,
the remaining children have an obligation to honor. This is the way
the רשב"ם Rashbam understands. They have to honor their mother, assuming his
wife is their mother, and they have to honor their older brother,
right? There's a דרשה Drasha the גמרא Gemara makes, כבד את אביך
ואת אמך, Kabeid Es Avicha V'Es Imecha, the extra את Es means
to include your older brother. Okay, so therefore, we understand that they
want to give them a certain position of authority and we're going
to read it that way and not a literally gifting of all
of the property. But now we've got some questions. Okay, so בנו
הקטן
מה? beno hakatan mah? What about the younger son or the youngest
or a younger son where there's no obligation on the other brothers
to honor a younger child? Okay, or not the oldest son. So
therefore there, right, like maybe he just wanted to give him all
the property. We don't read it in a context of we want
to give him a position of authority, okay, because why would you
want to give a younger child a position of authority? That's not
a natural thing. And therefore we're going to read it maybe literally:
he gifted it all. So the good thing, the point, well there's
two ironic things here. One ironic thing is that if you're giving
somebody all the property, let me tell you, the other members of
the family are going to treat that person with a heck of
a lot of deference if they're the ones that hold all the
purse strings. Number one, you know, not only control it but actually
own it. So number two though is that you actually in this
discussion want to be somebody
that you know is not seen as somebody that the person dying
would want to ensure that they get honored. Like you know if
oh it's only a younger son, yeah, I'll be happy to be
the younger son and get all the property rather than to be
assigned as an אפוטרופא. apotropa. You know what I mean? So like
somehow if you have a lesser status within the family, you wind
up better in this case, then it's not we're not going to
read it as being assigned a position of authority, we're going to
read it literally as being gifted all the property. Let's get a
little in, okay? So בנו הקטן מה? beno hakatan mah? So what
would be the story about a younger son? So איתמר, itmar, it
was said, רב חנילאי בר אידי אמר שמואל, Rav Chanilai bar Idi
amar Shmuel, so the first position was רב יהודה Rav Yehuda in
the name of שמואל. Shmuel. Here's רב חנילאי בר אידי Rav Chanilai
bar Idi in the name of שמואל. Shmuel. He would say אפילו
בנו הקטן המוטל בעריסה, afilu beno hakatan hamutal b'arisa, even if it
was a little infant baby in a crib, okay? So we are
so why would a guy want his little infant baby, like he
doesn't even relate to him yet in terms of his personality and
his status and his identity? So it was one thing to say
he wants to gift all of his property to his youngest son.
But he's thinking about this little baby is going to be the
executor, the estate. First of all, if he dies ten minutes from
now or ten days from now, how could this little baby be
the executor? And why would he want to give him a position
of authority? I mean it's different to want to give him a
gift. So it's obviously talk about הלכות סבלותיימה, hilchos sabloteima, we're just
going to read it this way, we're going to choose to read
it this way. Okay again, the benefit of reading it this way
is it doesn't undermine, it doesn't take away, disinherit everybody else. And
this is only when all the property is given this way. So
the גמרא Gemara says פשיטא, pshita, now so that we got now.
פשיטא, pshita, so now we're going to step back again and reassess
where we're at. פשיטא בנו ואחר, pshita beno v'acher, I get if
it's a son if you give gift all the property to a
son, contrast that with gifting all the property to a stranger. So
אחר במתנה, acher b'matana, if it's gifted all to a stranger we
read it as a gift. בנו אפוטרופא, beno apotropa, and the son
as we said, whether an older son or a younger son, you're
making the person the sort of overseer and the executor. Now I
just want to pause for a second that I just read it
as contrasting two scenarios. The רשב"ם Rashbam reads a possibility here that
we're talking about the same case. That the person says I'm giving
all of my property to my son and to שמעון Shimon over
there, my next door neighbor שמעון. Shimon. So that in that case
now it's right what we would say is we're going to say
שמעון Shimon gets his half as a gift, okay, because you gave
it all to the two of them. שמעון's Shimon half is a
gift. And now verse I want to when it comes to your
son, we're saying well what you wound up doing is after you
gifted half to שמעון, Shimon, what you wound up doing is giving
all of your remaining property that should be inherited by your children
all to one son. So that turns that into a case of
all of your property to one son. Okay, so therefore in that
case we would give half to שמעון Shimon and make ראובן Reuven
and get the other half and שמעון Shimon is this next door
neighbor and make the other half something that all of the heirs
inherit naturally and that your son is the executor. Okay, so that's
a more of a חידוש chiddush reading, right? You might think that
once you're not giving it all in one big lump to your
son, we would say half goes to your next door neighbor and
half goes to your son, it's a straight מתנה. matana. So there's
two ways how to read this: are we talking about in one
gift you did half and half, and even in that case you
would say the son is only an executor over his half and
that it really is is now inherited by the heirs? Or are
we saying no no, in that case each side would get half,
really get it as a gift, and what we're doing is we're
contrasting two cases: all to a next door neighbor, he gets it
all as a gift; all to your son, he gets it as
an אפוטרופא, apotropa, he's only the executor. I know you have a
question Michael, I'm reading a little more, I haven't forgotten about you.
Now let's read the stuff in the parentheses. אשה ואחר, isha v'acher,
similarly if we contrast giving it all to your wife or giving
it all to your next door neighbor. ואחר במתנה, v'acher b'matana, your
next door neighbor is a gift (your next door wife did I
just say that? your next door neighbor). Okay, your next door neighbor
is a gift, okay, ואשתו אפוטרופא, v'ishto apotropa, and when you give
it to your wife she's an executor. And again we could read
this as you gave them both of them all of the property,
and even in that case read it as an executor, but the
רשב"ם Rashbam prefers the read you're contrasting two cases: all to your
next door neighbor, he gets it all as a gift. gift, all
to your wife, אפוטרופוס. apotropus. Now, here though are the cases which
we don't know. So we've got a stranger, we've got your wife,
and we've got a son. How about the following case? אשתו ארוסה
ואשתו גרושה במתנה. Ishto arusa ve-ishto grusha be-matanah. Okay, so if however
it is a wife that is you're not yet married to her
fully, betrothed. You haven't done the ניסואין. nisuin. You haven't started living
together. You gave her the ring, she was I don't know, maybe
she's ten years old or something, and you haven't yet actually started
living together. In that case, we're going to read it as since
you have not yet, here's the irony, since you're not yet that
close to her because you haven't started living together, okay, we're not
going to read it as oh you want to make sure that
all the kids honor her or the heirs honor her or whatever,
we're going to read it as, you know, because there's a little
more distance, we're going to read it as the surface meaning as
a straight gift rather than as a position of authority and as
an אפוטרופוס. apotropus. That's your betrothed wife and all the more so
your divorced wife. Your divorced wife, of course, we're not going to
read it as oh you know you're so close to her you
want to give her a position of authority. That's the irony. So
rather than reading it, so because you're more distant from her, we're
going to read it as a gift rather than as an אפוטרופוס.
apotropus. Okay, so when it's not somebody you're as close to, it's
a gift. איבעיא להו. Ibay'a lehu. And here's the question. So we
got that. We got the cases where it's a gift, where you're
not so close, the cases where you are close as an אפוטרופוס.
apotropus. And here are the middle cases. איבעיא להו. Ibay'a lehu. בת
אצל בנים. Bat etzel banim.
Let's say you're giving it all to a daughter but you have
sons. All right? So should we say that you know there's no
reason the sons are responsible to honor a daughter. It would be
very bizarre from a societal context to סתם stam want to put
a daughter in a position of authority over the sons. Okay, so
that's a case where you might say it's not a position of
authority, you're literally gifting it. Okay, or maybe not. Maybe at the
end of the day it's your daughter, maybe you want to give
her a position of authority. בת אצל בנים. Bat etzel banim. ואשה
אצל אחים. Ve-ishah etzel achim.
Or let's say it was your wife and it wasn't that you
were leaving behind children. God, the guy was childless. He was leaving
behind brothers. So his brothers would have inherited from him. So would
we think that what he wants to do is he wants his
brothers to inherit and his wife to be the executor of the
estate and create a relationship where his brothers now have to have
deference to his wife and put his wife in a position of
authority? But that's bizarre. Why would a person like, it's one thing
within a nuclear family context. I want my wife to be the
head of the family, to be in a position of authority. I'm
going to make her אפוטרופוס. apotropus. I want one of my sons
to have that position vis-a-vis my others. Okay, but that you want
your wife to have a position of authority vis-a-vis your brothers?
Yes, if you think your brothers are going to squander your property.
Right, so that
so I understand.
Okay, for forty years I can trust her.
Oh okay, I hear that. That's a good point. You're right. So
that's looking at it as a question about who can you trust
and who is, who has business acumen. But then we would have
to check every case individually. We're making broad claims, you know. So
since we're making broad claims, right, let's say your brothers are much
better businessmen and your wife wastes money. It's like we're not assessing
each case individually. We're sort of making broad claims, which is why
this is הלכתא בלא טעמא hilchata belo ta'ama because how are we
interpreting your words against their פשט pshat based on these like broad
rules?
So some of these claims? Right? Some of these would have no
place at all, like
you know, like the cases we had earlier, for instance. Yeah. You
want to give it to one son, you know, I mean he
hasn't spoken to any of these other sons and they have like
this contentious
relationship and he like effectively disowned them and said get out of
my house, just get out of my house.
So would we still say that he's? Right, meaning why aren't we
looking into the other context? I know, that's what's so strange about
this. That's why הלכתא בלא טעמא hilchata belo ta'ama we like completely
ignore context, right? You would think that if you want to interpret
these words against their פשט, pshat, you need like a lot of
contextual and circumstantial like evidence, right? As opposed to no, in this
case we're always going to read it this way, in this case
we're always, like it's very strange. I know that's why הלכתא בלא
טעמא. hilchata belo ta'ama. Okay, but let's read the question. So one
is a daughter amongst brothers. Would we say you wanted a position,
her in a position of authority over, a wife against your brothers,
again we're talking even conceptually the same family, okay, ואשה אצל בני
הבעל ve-ishah etzel bnei ha-ba'al or a stepmother. Your wife and what
you're leaving behind are children from another wife. So would you want
to gift it to your wife? Is that how we're going to
read it, which is the פשט? pshat? Or are we going to
read it that you want to put her in a position of
authority? Now, in that case the רשבם Rashbam actually says that your
children are responsible to honor your wife even if not her mother.
Okay, that's part of כבד את אביך, kabed et avicha, your father's
wife. Okay, but nevertheless maybe that's not as natural to create that
type of a dynamic. Okay, so מהו? mahu? What's the
הלכה? halachah? רבינא אמר משמיה דרב. Ravina amar mishmeih de-Rav. רבינא משמיה
דרבא, Ravina mishmei de-Rava, אמר רבינא משמיה דרבא, amar Ravina mishmei de-Rava,
בכולהו לא קנה לבר מארוסה וגרושה. bekulho lo kana levar me-arusa u'grusha.
Okay, so the only case that it works is the case, I
mean, the only case, excuse me, not that it works, it's a
funny way of saying it, the only, well, the only case that
it's not an אפוטרופוס apotropos
and it's an actual gift like it sounds like is the divorced
wife and the betrothed wife. Those are ones that you really don't
have yet a full relationship with, and those we're going to read
as a gift. All these other three cases that we just raised,
which was daughter amongst brothers, wife
among, daughter versus your sons, a wife against your brothers, or a
what was the third one? Or a stepmother. All of those we're
going to read as an אפוטרופוס. apotropos. That yes, it's just a
position of authority, it's not a gift.
רב
אבירא משמיה דרבא Rav Avira mishmei de-Rava אמר, amar, בכולהו קני, bekulho
kani, in all of them it is a good, it does work,
it is a gift, לבר levar the case it's not a gift
is אשה אצל אחים, isha etzel achim, wife by brothers, ואשה אצל
בני הבעל, ve'isha etzel bnei habaal, or the stepmother. So they really
only disagree about one case. It's a funny way of saying it.
It sounds like everything except this, everything except this, but really, guys,
there's very little that's between them. Right, so here you have the
case about ארוסה וגרושה.
arusa
u'grusha. Okay,
here you have the case about אשה אצל אחים, isha etzel achim,
and אשה אצל בני הבעל. ve'isha etzel bnei habaal. Okay, and in
the middle you have a case about בת אצל הבנים. bat etzel
habanim.
So one says it works in everything, it's an אפוטרופוס apotropos except
so the only thing it works for, here I'll do the green,
meaning that it's a real קנין, kinyan, not an אפוטרופוס. apotropos. The
first opinion says it doesn't work for anything, the only thing it
works for that it's a real קנין kinyan is ארוסה וגרושה. arusa
u'grusha. The other one says it works, it works in, what was
the other way of phrasing it?
בכולהו קני bekulho kani except for.
It works for everything except for these two. So it works for
everything except for these two means it works for these three. So
really, right, everybody agrees it doesn't work, but it's an אפוטרופוס, apotropos,
it's an authority position, not a קנין kinyan by the wife vis-a-vis
your brothers or the wife versus the stepchildren. That's a position of
authority, not a קנין. kinyan. Okay, everybody else agrees that it's, it
is a קנין kinyan by ארוסה וגרושה arusa u'grusha because you're not
yet, you're not really close to them. One you never got close
to fully and the other you divorced. The debate is a daughter
amongst sons. Is that going to be, work or not work? That's
the case. Is that going to be a position of authority? Is
that really going to be a קנין? kinyan? So that's the one
case we're debating. Michael, you've been waiting to ask a question.
Yes, so the question is, it's been nice, if you will, rereading
his statements to make these people אפוטרופוס. apotropos. Yeah, but let's say
he really wants to do it. Like, how is he going to
ever show that he really wants to do it? You have to
do a קנין? kinyan?
Like, how, oh, how do you do an appointing of an אפוטרופוס?
apotropos?
No, no, no, but he really wants someone, one brother, to actually
really inherit.
He would give, he would
give
one tiny sliver to somebody, he would leave over one tiny sliver.
He says, I'm being מקנה makne to you everything except a square
inch of, whether it has to be קרקע karka or מטלטלין, metaltelin,
but everything except one dollar worth of ownership in X, Y, and
Z. So because the point here, because it's total, okay, because it's
total, that's now of course the funny thing is that most people,
I'm disinheriting all of you, I'm giving it all to someone else,
right? So you know, so again, maybe חז"ל Chazal wanted to like
temper that and say, you know, but yeah, the simple way to
avoid this, you know, one wonders, can you be explicit?
You say, ולא לשם אפוטרופוס, אלא לקנין ממש, v'lo leshem apotropos, ela
l'kinyan mamash, would that work? Maybe that could work too, but the
other way is not giving it totally. Okay, בעי רבא. ba'ei Rava.
Now Rava asked, and this is why we introduced this, to get
to this question, which was similar to the question we asked of
רב יוחנן בן ברוקה. Rav Yochanan ben Broka. Top of קל"א ע"ב
kuf lamed aleph bet עמוד א'. amud aleph. בברי היכי. be'bari heichi.
What would be the story if
somebody, we talked about deathbed here?
Well, that's exactly what we're asking. Until now we were talking about
deathbed. Okay, what would be the story if somebody did this, gifted
all of his property, not in a שכיב מרע shachiv mera context?
What would be the story? בשכיב מרע הוא דניחא ליה לאשתמועי מיליה.
be-shachiv mera hu de-nicha lei l'ishtamuei milei. So do we say that
it's on his deathbed where he basically feels like I'm about to
die and therefore I want my wife to be in a position
of authority, so I'm going to do this to put her in
this position of authority? אבל בברי הא קאי איהו. aval be-bari ha
kai ihu. But if he's alive, he figures like why do I
right now have to transfer all my property to my wife to
give her in a position of authority? I'm in the position of
authority and people are going to listen to me and she's my
wife, so they'll sort of listen to her in deference to me.
He's thinking right now, he's thinking to
take effect when I'm dead. Well, okay, so that's a good question
too. Does he want it to take effect... If you look at
the רשב״ם, Rashbam, he considers both cases. He says, שכתב כל נכסיו
לאשתו, shekatav kol nechasav leishto, כל הני דאמר שמואל, kol hanei de'amar
Shmuel, אם כתב לה במתנה מהיום לגמרי, im katav lah bematana mehayom
legamre, either a straight gift today, אי נמי מהיום ולאחר מיתה, ei
nami mehayom ule'achar mita, or beginning today but taking a full effect
after death. But even if it's מהיום ולאחר מיתה, mehayom ule'achar mita,
right,
alright, so then what's the question? So he says, מי אמרינן, mi
amrinan, here we might as well read it, מתנה גמורה היא, matana
gemura hi, it's a real gift, אי משום כבודא דהכא הוא ויכבדוה
מאמתה? ei mishum kvoda dehacha hu veychabduha me'amata? Then I'm still like,
if I just wanted to honor her, then if I just wanted
to make sure that they would show her deference, why would I
give her the property now or give her or have the property
ownership start now, right, like to honor her in deference to me?
So if I'm giving it, if I'm doing it now, it must
be that I'm really giving a gift.
Understood, some version is either מהיום לגמרי mehayom legamre or מהיום ולאחר
מיתה. mehayom ule'achar mita. Why today? Why not a second before I
die?
Right, so you could say that there's a middle case, a case
where you're doing it today, but you want it to take effect
before you die, and that's more likely to be in the שכיב
מרע shachiv mera category. You're anticipating your death and when you're not
around. So it could be we rule one way by a straight
ברי bari today, and another way by a ברי bari of מהיום
ולאחר מיתה. mehayom ule'achar mita. But anyway, but either of them, the
point is the fact that you're starting it today, okay, maybe is
an indication that you mean it as a real gift. Okay, או
דילמא, o dilma,
so, do we say that therefore if he's, if he's well, that
therefore it's a real gift, okay, he's not really anticipating him not
being, himself not being on the scene, או דילמא, o dilma, or
do we say, ברי נמי ניחא ליה דלישמעון מיליה מהשתא? bari nami
nicha lei delishme'un milei mehashta? No, even if you're alive and well,
you would like to start seeing your wife start, start being in
a position of authority and people deferring directly to her, not deferring
to her because she's your wife, deferring directly to her. And maybe
we're going to read it that way and therefore
they need to give her a little more respect.
Right. They're going to know that this, that she is going to
go ahead and be now the executor, right, of the estate. So
again, of course, the funny thing is that if she really knew
she was getting all the property, they would even more treat her
with deference. But okay, even if you're giving it as a gift
right now when you're healthy, we're going to read it in the
context of being an executor and not being an owner. Okay, so
what's the law? תא שמע, ta shema, come and hear. הכותב פירות
נכסיו לאשתו, hakotev perot nechasav leishto,
somebody goes ahead and writes, now you, so basically his wife has
a lien on his property to collect the כתובה, ketubah, okay. The
כתובה ketubah is the two hundred זוז, zuz, or whatever it is,
the standard amount of the כתובה, ketubah, plus if the wife brought
in any property in the dowry,
so the כתובה ketubah says that when the guy dies or if
he divorces you, you take out from his estate the value of
the property that you brought in in your dowry. Okay, that's the
value of the כתובה. ketubah. And so she has a lien on
all of his property to collect the כתובה ketubah when he dies
or if he divorces her. Okay. Everybody good? So now what this
guy did was, he basically took a piece of his property, okay,
here's the guy,
here's all of his fields that his wife has liens on, okay,
and with one of these fields he went ahead and, where are
we,
הכותב פירות נכסיו לאשתו. hakotev perot nechasav leishto. So he basically says
while he's, while they're married and while he's alive and well and
everything is good, hey hon, what I'm gonna do is I'm gonna
give you all of the פירות, perot, the produce of the field,
not the title of the field, the produce of the field, okay.
And the question is by her agreeing to accept the produce of
the field, do we read it as if she's waiving her liens
on this field? So if he went ahead now, maybe it was
the only field that he had, and sold the field, okay, could
she still go ahead and after he's dead collect the כתובה ketubah
or can the guy say the fact that you were willing to
take the fruit of the field was an implicit waiving of your
liens on it? Now that's a bizarre thing to say.
He has title, she has liens. Right, he has title, she has
liens, okay.
Here she is. Okay. So he first gives her this, but she's
got liens on it. So do we say that her agreeing to
take that is a waiving of her liens? The answer is no,
we, okay. Now
הכותב פירות נכסיו לאשתו גובה כתובתה מן הקרקע, hakotev perot nechasav leishto
gova ketubata min hakarka, she can still collect her כתובה ketubah from
the field, she does not have waived her liens. למחצה לשליש
ולרביע, lemechetza lishlish uleravia, let's say he gave her not the פירות,
perot, he said I'm actually gifting you half of that field or
a third or a quarter, do we say that the fact she
was gifted half of the field means she's waiving her liens on
the other part, okay. And the answer also is going to be
no. By the way, another parenthetical question is, do we say when
a person gives property to his wife, to his wife, that we
implicitly read it as a partial payment of the כתובה ketubah or
not? Okay, so there's another גמרא gemara that's going to be say
that we're going to normally assume we're going to read this as
a partial
payment. But even if that were true, maybe even all the more
so, if this is worth half of her כתובה, Kesuvah, she's not
waiving her rights on the other half. Fine, she got that, she's
still owed the rest of her כתובה, Kesuvah, or maybe he still
owes her whole כתובה, Kesuvah, and just because she got half a
field, she's not waiving her rights on the other half, yes?
So, would we ask the same question, the גמרא Gemara asks the
same question, forget about a marriage, but how about in a loan
situation?
Yeah, it would not, you're right. So we're going to get to
that later. That we're going to, we're going to be a little
more inclined to assume in the husband-wife context he's waiving her כתובה
Kesuvah rights. Okay, and you would think, isn't that strange, the whole
point of the כתובה Kesuvah is to protect the woman. I know,
it's a really good question.
Right, right, the הוה אמינא Hava Amina here, we would never have
a הוה אמינא Hava Amina about this in a loan, and you're
going to get more upset later because we're going to have cases
where she actually is interpreted to waive her rights. Okay? So, and
it's strange. The
גמרא Gemara is going to say מכולי כתובה שנו כאן. mikulei kesuvah
shanu kan. It's a special leniency of the כתובה, Kesuvah, yeah, leniency
for the man, not for the woman, lean,
haha. Okay, anyway, so it says like this: Now in those cases,
גובה כתובתה מן השאר. gova kesuvatah min hashear. She gets it from
the rest. Now, כתב כל נכסיו לאשתו. kasav kol nechasav leishto. Let's
say he granted her all of his property. Including, well, let's not
worry about the מטלטלין metaltelin right now. Okay, and
now, so you would say, okay, she got all the property then
why is it relevant, who cares if she still has a lien
or not? There's nothing left to collect. Okay, no. Now what happened
was is he died, and יצא עליו שטר חוב. yatza alav shtar
chov.
Now, okay, he gave all of the property to the wife,
okay? Ignore the פירות. peiros. She now, well, we don't know that.
The פשט pshat of this משנה Mishnah is she's not an אפוטרופא.
apotropa. Okay, so this, well, that's what we're going to try to
prove. He gave all of it to his wife, okay? Great. So
what's left to happen? There's no property left to collect the כתובה.
Kesuvah. No, comes along this guy who the husband owed money to
and he said: Right, what do you mean? It's very nice now
that your wife owns all of your property. What are you trying
to do, hide it away from me? You know, so put it
in your wife's name? You owe me a thousand dollars. Okay, so
that's no different than a gift. What would be if this guy
gifted his property to somebody? I've got a lien. You owed me
a thousand dollars. I'm going to go ahead and take that field.
I've got a lien on it to pay up my debt. Exactly,
exactly, exactly. So I'm going to go ahead and take it and
pay my debt. So now the wife can come along and say,
oh, okay, that's fine. But you know what? He borrowed money from
you after we got married. And when we first got married, I
had a prior, I had the first lien. And the day we
got married, I had a lien on all of his property for
the payment of the כתובה. Kesuvah. Then he borrowed money from you,
your lien comes after mine. The person with the earliest lien wins
out. Okay?
So doesn't matter, that maybe that wasn't payment of the כתובה. Kesuvah.
Even if it was payment of the כתובה, Kesuvah, maybe it's now
not fully paid, maybe it hasn't been fully, right, maybe there's a
leftover, okay? So she says, very nice, you took it. I still
have my lien on that property from way back when we got
married, I'm going to be able to take it away from you.
So what the man had to do to become a debtor
and protect all of his property is get married.
In other words, because he's getting married, no לקוח lokeiach can like
even exercise his right.
Well, you can always hide your... no, because her lien is only
good enough for the value of the כתובה. Kesuvah. But for all
of that, right, exactly. Okay, so that's what it says. So in
that case, so what would happen? Would you say that when he
gifted all the property, that is going to be read as a
waiving of her liens? Or does she still retain her lien even
if all the property's been gifted to her? Okay, yes I own
it all now, but at the same time that I own it,
I still have a prior lien on it. So when this guy
comes and takes it, I'm going to be able to take it
away from him. Do we say her taking all of the property
is a waiving of her liens? Okay, so that's a debate. רבי
אליעזר אומר תכור מתנתה ותעמוד כתובתה. Rabbi Eliezer omer tichur matnasah vesaamod
kesuvatah. She has to... now this is not literal, but it's figurative.
You know, pretend like you never got the gift and now collect
your כתובה. Kesuvah. The fact that you got... the way of saying
it is, you still have your liens. The fact that you got
your gift does not mean that you've given up your lien. And
the חכמים chachamim say, and the חכמים chachamim say, no, תכור כתובתה
ותעמוד מתנתה. tichur kesuvatah vesaamod matnasah. I'm sorry, I'm sorry, you've taken
a gift, so that means and you took all of his property
as a gift, that meant that you waived your כתובה Kesuvah rights.
Okay? Tear it up, tear it up. Okay, now it's figurative. Okay,
now, ונמצא קרח מכאן ומכאן, venimtzah kereach mikan umikan, and you lose
and you're bald from both ends. Now, I don't exactly get what
it means that you're bald from both ends, I mean only on
the... One end, you got the rest of the property, but it
means, I'm sorry honey, you thought you were going to get a
מתנה matanah and it was going to be great and you were
going to get all this property, and the way it actually works
out, because let's say, imagine that his actual lien was actually for
all the property. Okay, so you thought you were going to get
a gift, what happened now is this creditor came, took away your
gift because he had a lien, that's I guess that's one קרחה,
karachah, you're bald because your gift has been taken away, and you'll
say, well at least let me collect my כתובה. ketubah. No, you're
bald at that side too because you've lost your כתובה, ketubah, you
lost your כתובה ketubah and you lost your gift.
Does the גמרא Gemara want women to become bald?
I guess so. Okay, anyway, so דאמר רב יהודה, d'amar Rav Yehuda,
said רב יהודה הנחתום, Rav Yehuda HaNachtom, רב יהודה Rav Yehuda the
baker, okay, מעשה שאירע דבר בבת אחותי כלה. maaseh she'ira davar bevat
achoti kallah. This happened to my, to my niece, my sister's
daughter who was my daughter-in-law. כלה kallah doesn't mean a, like a
bride, it means my daughter-in-law. So basically my son married my niece,
they, cousins married, okay. And so this happened to her that apparently
he's saying that his son died and after his son had gifted
all of the property to his wife, okay, and then the creditors
came. Okay, בא מעשה לפני חכמים ואמרו תקרע כתובתה ותעמוד על מתנתה,
ba maaseh lifnei chachamim veamru tikra ketuvatah vetaamod al matanatah,
I'm sorry, yada yada yada, you gotta give up your כתובה, ketubah,
you gotta just accept your gift, whatever's left of it, ונמצאת קרחת
מכאן ומכאן, venimtza kereach mikan umikan, and you're bald on both sides.
Okay, so your taking of all the property is a waiving of
your כתובה ketubah rights. And as Dov said we would never say
it by a normal creditor, right, if I gifted all my property
to a normal creditor we wouldn't say it's a waiving of rights,
somehow in the dynamics between husband and wife sometimes we're more prepared
to say that, which is quite ironic since the whole point of
a כתובה ketubah is to protect the woman's interest, okay, but there's
also the husband's interest and the גמרא Gemara is always yelling with
the fact that if we are too demanding about what the husband's
obligations are to the wife or what her rights are, then they'll
hesitate before getting married, so it's like this balancing act of protecting
the wives enough that their interests are protected, but not enough that
it scares men away from getting married. So that's sometimes the logic
behind it. Anyway, the point is, for us is, he gifted all
the property and it was a gift, it wasn't just that she
was an אפוטרופוס, apotropus, so you see that there's a scenario where
you can gift all your property to your wife and it works
as a real gift, so presumably that's the difference between whether you're
doing it as a well person, as a healthy person, or as
someone on their deathbed, because if this applied even to a healthy
person, why would she own the property? She would just be an
אפוטרופוס. apotropus. So that's why we're bringing this in. טעמא דיצא עליו
שטר חוב, taama deyatzah alav shetar chov, the reason that this thing
becomes complicated and she might lose the property is because a creditor
came with a debt. הא לא יצא עליו שטר חוב קנייה, ha
lo yatzah alav shetar chov kanyah, had that happened, she would own
all the property. ובמאי? ubemai? Now what's the case? אילימא בשכיב מרע,
ilima beshkiv mera,
if the guy gifted it to his wife when he was on
his deathbed, הא אמרת לא עשאה אפוטרופוס, ha amart lo asa'ah apotropus,
we said that's only an אפוטרופוס. apotropus. So אלא לאו בברי, ella
lav bevari, it must be that he was healthy and therefore you
see that this law that she's made an אפוטרופוס apotropus and it's
not a gift applies only to a guy on his deathbed, doesn't
apply to a healthy guy because here it really is a gift,
pretty good proof. So the גמרא Gemara says no, לאו בשכיב מרע,
lav beshkiv mera, I could say that we're talking about a guy
on his deathbed, or really meaning another way of saying it is
it wouldn't matter, maybe this law applies whether on your deathbed, whether
you're healthy, that it's an אפוטרופוס. apotropus. So why does she really
own it? Because there's another exception to the law. What's the other
exception? The other exception is, so ורב אבירא מוקי לה בכולהו, veRav
Avira moki lah bechulhu, ורבינא מוקי לה באשה ארוסה ובאשה
גרושה. veRavina moki lah beisha arusah uveisha gerushah. Remember here are other
exceptions to the law, right? Where does it not apply? It doesn't
apply if your wife is only betrothed or your wife is already
divorced. So maybe this case where he gifted it all to his
wife and then she wanted to collect her כתובה ketubah was that
she was a divorced wife already or she was an ארוסה, arusah,
and that's why we're going to read it as a literal gift.
Okay, but maybe if whether he's healthy or on his deathbed it'll
be an אפוטרופוס, apotropus, and the reason this is a gift is
not because he was healthy, the reason this is a gift is
because his wife was an ארוסה arusah or גרושה. gerushah. All right,
so we didn't prove it, although it would have seemed like a
pretty nice proof. Okay, אמר רב יוסף בר מניומי אמר רב נחמן,
amar Rav Yosef bar Minyomi amar Rav Nachman, הלכה, halachah, now that
we brought in this question about what happens when it's all gifted
and then the creditor comes and so on, we're going to have
a rule on it. The הלכה halachah is
תקרע כתובתה ותעמוד על מתנתה ונמצאת קרחת מכאן ומכאן. tikra ketuvatah vetaamod
al matanatah venimtza kereach mikan umikan. Sorry honey, that's a rule of
חכמים. chachamim. Okay, your taking of the gift is read as a
waiving of your liens and therefore you lost your gift and now
you lost your כתובה.
ketubah. What was Rav Avira doing saying before? I
don't know.
It wound up to be the same. He says it applies, it
applies to these three cases. But of course we're not talking about
the case of בת בנים ומשפחתי Bat Banim uMishpachtay obviously, it's all
that. Okay, so okay, so that's the story, it's read as a
waive of your liens. Now by the way, the רשב"ם Rashbam does
point out, although this is not at all explicit in the גמרא
Gemara until tomorrow and you could say it's debated, but the רשב"ם
Rashbam says it's a waving of your current liens. If the husband
gets property later, she gets liens on later acquired property. But it's
a waving of all of the liens on the property that she
just received, okay?
The כתובה ketubah remains in effect.
Yes, he still owes her the money. She just waives the liens
on the property that she received, okay? But A, he owes her
the money, so certainly if there's like, you know, if he paid
her off, if it was a גרושה, gerusha, he hadn't died yet,
he would pay her off from cash. And number two is, even
if he died and it's only an issue of liens, if he
acquired any real estate afterwards, she would get liens on the real
estate later. But she waives the liens on the real estate that
she received just here.
Wait, so that means let's say he doesn't acquire any other property.
Right, so he gets the, but other creditors meanwhile came and they...
she's given up her liens on the קרקע. karka. But then they
get divorced. So the כתובה ketubah still has legal force and he
has to pay her from cash?
Yes. Cash. If it's a divorce, then it's like anybody who owes
you money and even if they don't have any real estate, they
have to pay you cash or they have to pay you מטלטלין.
metaltelin. But if he dies, if he dies, then it's only in
the hands of the heirs and then she can only exercise liens
on real estate, okay? Until the גאונים Geonim came and changed it.
Okay, so the פשט pshat of תיקרע כתובתה... Tikrei ketuvatah...
right, it's not literally תיקרע כתובתה. Tikrei ketuvatah. It means you've lost
your liens on this property, on that property. Right, at least that's
what's going to develop later. Whether that's maybe this is making a
stronger statement, but the רשב"ם Rashbam reads it in context of the
later discussion. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay,
ונמצאת קרחת מכאן ומכאן. venimtset kerachat mikan umikan. So the גמרא Gemara
says למימרא דלא אזיל רב נחמן בתר אומדנא? Lemeimra d'lo azil Rav
Nachman batar umdana? Now, if you're saying רב נחמן Rav Nachman says
that we're going to read it as a waving of her liens,
so now what you're telling me is that רב נחמן Rav Nachman
does not go by an אומדנא. umdana. אומדנא Umdana is trying to
assess somebody's intent. Now, this is a strange point because you would
say the person who reads it as a waving of liens דוקא
davka is assessing a person's intent. If you only went by what
was on the surface, so she accepted a gift, she never explicitly
waived her liens. So we don't read it as a waving of
liens. I'm not going to try to guess what's in your mind,
you know? You didn't waive your liens, you just accepted a gift.
So but the גמרא Gemara is saying... the fact that he's reading
it as a waving of liens shows רב נחמן Rav Nachman goes...
excuse me, this shows that רב נחמן Rav Nachman doesn't go by
what's in her head. What do you mean? It shows that he
is going by what's in her head. All right, so let's read
the case that the גמרא Gemara brings to prove it and I'll
try to explain where I think the גמרא Gemara is coming from.
We used that language already earlier in the previous עמוד. amud.
אומדנא, Umdana, right. That's all these cases. Exactly, when we're reading a
gift as making somebody not a בר פחיתא, bar pachita, what we're
doing is we're going by אומדנא, umdana, we're trying to get into
the person's head.
And that's classic for שכיב מרע shechiv mera in
general.
Well,
yeah, the classic שכיב מרע shechiv mera is that we create an
institution that allows him to gift things verbally, okay? But, but here
anyway, the general rule of all that we're doing when we're going
and not interpreting the words on their surface meaning is we're going
by אומדנא, umdana, we're getting in the person's head. So if you
actually say she waived the liens, that would actually be like saying
that you are going by אומדנא. umdana. So why does the גמרא
Gemara say you're not going by אומדנא? umdana? So let's read what
case the גמרא Gemara is contrasting this to, okay? דתניא, De-tanya, we
taught in a ברייתא: braita: הרי שהלך בנו למדינת הים. Harei she-halach
bno l'medinat hayam. Reuven's son went to China to make his fortune
in the world, okay? ושמע שמת בנו, Veshamah shemet bno, and when
he got back, a report that tragically Reuven died in China and
he assumed it was true and after hearing that, הוא עמד וכתב
כל נכסיו לאחרים. hu amad ve-katav kol nechasav l'acherim. He got up
and he didn't verbally say 'I am giving it now to my
next-door neighbor because I think my son is dead,' okay? But that's
what happened, that was the sequence. He heard his son was dead
and the next day he wrote it all as a gift to
his next-door neighbor, all right? So it's not so hard to figure
out what was probably in his mind when he was doing it,
although he didn't articulate. ואחר כך בא בנו. ve-achar kach ba bno.
And then his son came back, okay? Turned out it was all
a false rumor.
Rumors of his death have been...
exactly. So מתנתו מתנה. matnato matanah. Okay, it's still a gift. He
didn't explicitly say he was giving it because he was making certain
assumptions. So we just go by the surface thing. It was a
gift without any conditions, the gift remains binding. רב שמעון בן מנסיא
Rav Shimon ben Menasya ר' שמעון בן מנסיא אומר, Rebbe Shimon ben
Menasya omer, but ר' שמעון בן מנסיא Rebbe Shimon ben Menasya says,
אין מתנתו מתנה. ein matnato matana. No, his gift is not binding.
שאילו היה יודע שבנו קיים, she'ilu haya yodeia shebeno kayam, had he
known that his son was alive, לא כתבן, lo katavan, he would
not have written them. So we interpret it—I know, that's going by
אומדנא. umdena. Right. So some cases are obvious, some cases are less
obvious. That's why the law usually likes things to be explicit because
how and let's say he waited two and a half weeks before
writing it and how do you figure that out? But that's, ר'
שמעון בן מנסיא Rebbe Shimon ben Menasya says I am prepared to
look contextually and to say if it seems obvious to the בית
דין beis din that that was his mindset, that will determine the
context in which he gave it and since he was mistaken, the
gift is not good. And that's going by אומדנא. umdena. We're going
by what we're assessing his intent to be and not just by
the surface exchange, okay? Now, and we know that דאמר רב נחמן
הלכה כר' שמעון בן מנסיא, d'amar Rav Nachman halacha k'Rebbe Shimon ben
Menasya, we rule like ר' שמעון בן מנסיא. Rebbe Shimon ben Menasya.
So there Rav Nachman goes by אומדנא. umdena. Why doesn't he go
by אומדנא umdena here? Now, again, what do you mean? He is
going by אומדנא umdena here. He's reading the wife as having been
מוחל, mochel, giving up her lien. No, but it seems like the
point of—we're making a particular point. We're saying going by an אומדנא
umdena so that when we will read that if you are mistaken
about the context or possibly mistaken about the context, that we're going
to say you never would have wanted to do it. So what
we're going to say is the following: everybody is going to agree
that on the surface, accepting a gift is an implicit waiving of
liens. Why do I need liens? If I got all the property,
who needs the liens? I got the property itself. So everybody assumes
that that's obvious, that's just waiving of liens. The question is, wait,
were you thinking of the possibility that there might be a creditor?
So that's like having a mistake about whether the son is alive
or not. Are we going to say that, oh, had she been
thinking of the possibility of a creditor, she wouldn't have waived her
liens? So if she did waive her lien, it was a mistake
because she wasn't thinking about it, like the mistake of the guy
who thought his son was dead and his son was alive.
Okay, that makes sense, except it's a first lien that they actually
own the property.
In this case, but you didn't realize it at the time. So
that's the question: if ר' יוחנן Rebbe Yochanan goes like ר' שמעון
בן מנסיא Rebbe Shimon ben Menasya and says we will say that
if you hadn't been thinking of a possibility
and had you been thinking of it and had you realized the
facts or realized the possibility you wouldn't have wanted to do it,
we will use that to define the context of what you did.
So let's say the same here: had she been realizing that there
was a creditor she wouldn't have given it up, let's use that
to say she didn't give it up. So now we understand the
question. So the גמרא Gemara says
no, שאני התם דניחא לה דתיפוק לה קלא דכתבינהו ניהלה הני נכסי.
shani hatam d'nicha leh d'teipok leh kala d'kasvinuh nihaleh hani nechasim. No,
here it's different. Here she was willing, we'll say, even if somebody
had said to her at the time, "Hey, wait, you shouldn't take
that gift because there might be a creditor and the creditor will
come and take it away and then you'll be קרח מכאן ומכאן
karach mikan u-mikan or whatever. You want to think twice before taking
that gift." She might have said, or we're going to imagine she
would say, "You know what? Even if it's possible there is a
creditor, I don't care. I want this gift now because the fact
that right now I am taking this gift, everybody thinks I'm this
important woman, I just got all of my husband's property." So I
am willing to take it with that risk involved,
recognizing the risk that the taking of it is a waiving of
liens and I might wind up losing out. So when the guy
goes and gifts all his property to his next-door neighbor, she
wouldn't—he's not willing to do it knowing there's a risk that his
son might be alive. If he for one second thought his son
might be alive, he never would have done it. Okay, there was
no gain for him to do it. Whereas here, she would have
been prepared to do it even had she considered the possibility that
there might be a creditor. Had she known, that would have been
different maybe. But even had she considered it, she accepted it with—we'll
say she would have accepted it knowing the risk. Now of course
what you could say is she would have accepted the property but
she wouldn't have waived the lien. All right, somehow we're seeing that
as a package deal. Okay, she would have been prepared to accept
it even if it included an implicit waiving of liens even knowing
the risk because it was in her interest to accept it right
now.
Okay, and that's—the סברא svara is that she understands that she'd be
waiving the lien. Right. Worth it though.
Right, although you could say, "No, then I would have accepted it
without waiv—" like why we have to bundle it is not clear.
But anyway, that's how we reconcile. Now I do want to say—I
do want to say one thing about, by the way, about this
idea of going by אומדנא, umdena, and that's also relevant to all
of these cases, right? We take something as a gift and we
reread it. Like, what is that? Why? Don't we have a general
principle? I mean, this is
what's the general principle? The general principle is דברים שבלב אינם דברים.
Devarim she-be-lev einam devarim.
You don't go by what you think is in somebody's head. You
go by what somebody explicitly said. And here, everything is trying to
get into the person's head and to reread what they did. Right?
So what's going on here? What about דברים שבלב? Devarim she-be-lev? So
נדרים Nedarim is like, well,
נדרים Nedarim is
different, but there's one way in which it's similar. But certainly in
transactions and דיני ממונות, dinei mamonot, you say you go by what
somebody said, not by what they're thinking. And here we're all trying
to go by what somebody is thinking. So תוספות רי"ד Tosafot Rid
says explicitly what I'm about to say. רמב"ם Rambam says it implicitly.
רמב"ם Rambam says in הלכות מכירה, Hilchos Mechira, רמב"ם Rambam says דברים
שבלב אינם דברים. Devarim she-be-lev einam devarim. In הלכות מתנה, Hilchos Matana,
רמב"ם Rambam says לעולם אומדין le-olam omdin with an אלף, alef, דעת
הנותן. da'as ha-noten. You always try to determine what the person is
thinking. And he gives this case of the guy who thought his
son was dead. So what's the difference? The difference is between מכירה
mechira and מתנה. matana. A two-sided transaction, you're paying something for my
car, we cannot say that it matters what I'm thinking. It's not
fair to you.
It's two-sided, you're willing to give money. The only thing that we
can sort of say determines it to be fair to all sides
is things that are stated explicitly. Okay. Whereas if I'm gifting something
to you, you're just a receiver. Right? So you didn't do anything
to merit my gift. Okay. And therefore, it's not going to be
unfair to you. I mean, you might not like it if we
qualify my gift based on what's in my head. Okay. But it's
not the same need that everything be external and objective and accessible.
הלכה Halacha is more prepared to try to understand what is the
context of what I'm thinking. So almost all these cases here are
one-sided transactions. A gift of all the property to the wife, right,
a gift to the next-door neighbor because he thought his son was
dead. In those types of cases, we are willing to look a
little bit deeper into what a person might be thinking because it's
one-sided rather than saying it's, no, דברים שבלב אינם דברים. Devarim she-be-lev
einam devarim. All right. So that's an important way to understand what
the dynamics here is, what this is about. Okay. Let's keep on
going. תנן התם. Tnan hatam.
No, but in one case we're talking about what the
woman is thinking, the other one we're talking about what the person
is giving over the gift.
Right. So the one case that doesn't work so well is this
because she received it, but what we're saying is it is more
transactional. Because she received it, we're going to read it as a
waiving of her rights. So this case is more two-sided. Right? Because
they're asking why aren't they still protected as ארוס?
arus?
Right.
Well, that we're going to see. So let's reread this in this
case and at least turn the דף. daf. Okay. תנן התם. Tnan
hatam. We taught over there. הכותב נכסיו לבניו וכותב לאשתו קרקע כלשהו.
Ha-kosev nechasav le-vanav ve-chosev le-ishto karka kol shehu. A person is now
distributing all of his
property. And again, we'll assume deathbed, but we might want to question
that later. He's on his deathbed, he's distributing all of his property,
gifting it to all of his kids, maybe as a שכיב מרע,
shchiv mera, and then he gives his wife a little piece of
property. Okay. Worth I don't know, a hundred bucks. Okay. So אבדה
כתובתה. avda kesuvatah. She now has lost the rest of her כתובה.
kesuvah. So now somehow, even though her כתובה kesuvah was worth ten
thousand dollars and he gave her a hundred dollar piece of property,
she now has given up the rights to her כתובה. kesuvah.
Well, she, well we'll see about that. So the גמרא Gemara says
משום דכתב לה קרקע כלשהו אבדה כתובתה? mishum de-chasav lah karka kol
shehu avda kesuvatah? Because he gave her a little piece of land,
she lost her כתובה? kesuvah? אמר
רב במזכה על ידה. Amar Rav be-mizakeh al yadah. No, she was
an active participant in this distribution of property. So he basically calls
his wife over and says what we're going to do is with
a קניין. kinyan. Okay. We're going to see cases where שכיב מרע
shchiv mera is it just verbal, does it also have a קניין
kinyan in some cases? So he calls his wife over and he
says, "Okay, here's how we're going to do it. Now take this
handkerchief and be קונה koneh for ראובן Reuven this plot, my son
ראובן Reuven this plot of land. Take the handkerchief and now be
קונה koneh for שמעון Shimon this plot of land. Take for the
handkerchief be קונה koneh for לוי Levi this plot of land. And
now to take the handkerchief and be or whatever, I'll take your,
actually it's not you don't take the handkerchief, I take the handkerchief
because he's the giver so he gets the handkerchief from her. Give
me your handkerchief and I'll give ראובן Reuven this. Give me your
handkerchief and I'll give שמעון Shimon this. Give me your handkerchief and
I'll give you this little piece of land." So she's an active
participant in the whole process. Okay. And therefore what we read it
is, she's basically saying she's okay with it. She recognizes what the
husband is doing is basically saying this is what everybody gets. You
get what you get and you don't get upset. Okay. This is
what everybody gets. And I'm giving ראובן Reuven this and שמעון Shimon
this and you this little piece. And since she's actively participating and
showing she's okay with it, she's implicitly saying my whole the whole
thing I'm going to get out of my estate, even though I'm
entitled to my whole כתובה, kesuvah, I'm okay with the fact that
all I'm getting out of my estate is the... little piece of
land.
You have to understand נחת רוח עשיתי לבעלי. Nachas Ruach asiti l'baali.
Okay, so that's why we need two things happening here. Number one
is she has to actually get something. If she got nothing, then
she could say I wasn't waiving my rights. Okay, and that there
actually has to be an active
participation. Okay, but that's exactly what the גמרא Gemara is doing, it's
trying to limit the scope of this.
Okay, so she's no longer considered to be the first lien on
all the properties that he's...
right, we read all of this as essentially waiving her liens, waiving
her rights. Okay.
Cause if only one of these things
happened, we could have said נחת רוח. Nachas Ruach. Right, if she
either participated and didn't get property or got property and didn't participate,
then it would not. But because of both, we read this again
as a waiving of her liens. Okay, so that's answer number one.
ושמואל אמר במחלק לפניה והיא שותקת. U'Shmuel amar b'machalek l'faneha v'hi shotekes.
No, she doesn't have to actively participate. She just has to passively
be okay. He is distributing the property and she's not saying, wait,
what about my כתובה? Ketubah? When am I going to collect my
כתובה Ketubah from? Even silence in her presence, that's considered like being
okay with it. And that she receives something. רבי יוסי ברבי חנינא
אומר באומר לה טלי קרקע זה בכתובתך. Rabbi Yossi b'Rabbi Chanina omer
b'omer lah teli karka zeh b'kesuvaseich. That what he says to her
is, take this piece... maybe he distributed not in her presence. But
all he says to her was, and this little piece of land
will be your כתובה Ketubah payment. And she accepted it silently. Okay,
and the fact that she accepted it silently, that's implicitly saying I
accept this as my full payment of my כתובה. Ketubah. Now of
course you could imagine the husband is there on the deathbed and
he's about to die or whatever, and she doesn't want to start
getting into an argument with him and being embarrassed in front of
the other people or whatever, right, there could be a lot of
reasons and pressures or whatever she's not saying anything. But we're going
to read, these are three different answers, okay, and these are all
different ways of saying that it's in this context we're going to
read it as a waiving of her rights. And here comes the
kicker and this goes back to what we were discussing earlier, ומקולי
כתובה שנו כאן. u'mikulei Ketubah shanu kan.
Yes, this is bizarre, we would never say such a thing about
a normal creditor that if you somehow distribute property or whatever, you
know, but because this is a leniency, a leniency for the husband,
okay, that there are some cases where we're going to be more
ready to say the wife gave up on her כתובה Ketubah rights,
on her... and again, that's partly as we said a dynamic of
trying to protect the woman but also ensure that the husbands, men
are willing to get married. Okay, so that's basically the answer. We
will pick up tomorrow with challenging this question about does she always
waive it so readily or maybe you know maybe she's not really
waiving it so readily. Okay, so we'll continue with this tomorrow.